<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Chris Eidhof</title>
    <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Chris Eidhof</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Race Report: Berlin Marathon</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/race-report-berlin-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/race-report-berlin-marathon/</guid>
      <description>In 2015, I ran the Berlin Marathon in just under three hours: 2:59:41. It was my fourth attempt at the marathon. Even though I hit the wall at km 34, I had run the first bit fast enough to still make it under three hours. Before the race, I believed I could run under three hours, but actually doing so was a really magical feeling.
Berlin 2015: Still ran 2:59</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swift Analytics</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-analytics/</guid>
      <description>There have been a number of blog posts about the best way to do analytics in Swift:
 John writes about using enums. Matt writes about using structs. Dave writes about using protocols. Soroush writes about subclasses.  Krzysztof asked about whether I would do a function-based version.
I think all solutions are valid. They&amp;rsquo;re different embeddings of the same problem. Another version to consider is the simplest one: just inlining the network calls into your code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Micro Auto Layout DSL</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/micro-autolayout-dsl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/micro-autolayout-dsl/</guid>
      <description>These days, I&amp;rsquo;m using fewer external libraries. First, I don&amp;rsquo;t like most Swift libraries out there, they&amp;rsquo;re often implemented in a complicated way and contain too many protocols for my taste. Second, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how they&amp;rsquo;ll be maintained in the future, and most libraries are pretty big &amp;ndash; I don&amp;rsquo;t really want to own that code. Third, I&amp;rsquo;m too lazy to set up a dependency manager, so I&amp;rsquo;ll keep my projects dependency-free.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Struct References</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/references/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/references/</guid>
      <description>The full code for this is available as a gist.
 Recently I was trying to find a good use for Swift&amp;rsquo;s new keypaths. This post shows one example that accidentally came up. This is something I&amp;rsquo;ve researched, and not something I&amp;rsquo;ve used in production code. That said, I think it&amp;rsquo;s very cool and I&amp;rsquo;d like to show it.
Consider a simple address book application. It contains a table view with people, and a detail view controller which shows a Person instance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reducers</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/reducers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/reducers/</guid>
      <description>This blogpost is part of an upcoming project, more about that soon.
 Reducers are a way to deal with state changes, and are great for dealing with asynchronous code. They come in a number of different ways, and are used in architectures like Redux, Elm, Flux and more.
Instead of giving a definition up front, we&amp;rsquo;ll look refactor an example app that is well-suited to write with reducers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classes That Conform To Protocols</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/classes-and-protocols/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/classes-and-protocols/</guid>
      <description>The other day, someone asked how to have a variable which stores a UIView that also conforms to a protocol. In Objective-C, you would simply write UIView&amp;lt;HeaderViewProtocol&amp;gt;. In current Swift, you can&amp;rsquo;t write something like that. This posts shows two workarounds.
First, let&amp;rsquo;s set the stage, and assume we have a HeaderViewProtocol:
protocol HeaderViewProtocol { func setTitle(_ string: String) }  Until generalized existentials arrive, we&amp;rsquo;ll have to make do with a workaround.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Types vs TDD</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/types-vs-tdd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/types-vs-tdd/</guid>
      <description>This morning, I read an article against static typing. To be more precise: it argues against static typing in the way Swift/Kotlin implement it. I don&amp;rsquo;t know anything about Kotlin, so I&amp;rsquo;ll try to relate everything to Swift. The main point of the article is that too much static typing is a bad thing. I agree: although my definition of &amp;ldquo;too much&amp;rdquo; is very different.
The main point of critique is that we can&amp;rsquo;t possibly keep adding features to a language to solve actual problems, because we would end up with too many features.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protocol Oriented Programming is Not a Silver Bullet</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/protocol-oriented-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/protocol-oriented-programming/</guid>
      <description>In Swift, protocol-oriented programming is in fashion. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of Swift code out there that&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;protocol-oriented&amp;rdquo;, some open-source libraries even state it as a feature. I think protocols are heavily overused in Swift, and oftentimes the problem at hand can be solved in a much simpler way. In short: don&amp;rsquo;t be dogmatic about using (or avoiding) protocols.
One of the most influential sessions at WWDC 2015 was called Protocol-Oriented Programming in Swift.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Burnout</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/burnout/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/burnout/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a number of blogposts and talks recently that talk about depression, burn-out, and other mental problems. One post recommended reading a book. Another one recommended talking to friends and family. These things might help, but I doubt that they actually solve the root cause (looking back, they definitely didn&amp;rsquo;t solve my problems, at best suppress them).
I recommend something different. If you have a mental issue, go see a professional.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Type Erasers in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/type-erasers-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/type-erasers-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>The following post is an excerpt from our book Advanced Swift. We just updated it to Swift 3, so this is a great time to buy it.
Sometimes, we can use a protocol as a standalone type. However, with a protocol like IteratorProtocol, this isn&amp;rsquo;t (yet) possible, because it has an associated type. The compile error says: &amp;ldquo;Protocol &amp;lsquo;IteratorProtocol&amp;rsquo; can only be used as a generic constraint because it has Self or associated type requirements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sort Descriptors in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/sort-descriptors-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/sort-descriptors-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>Just last week, someone asked me &amp;ldquo;in what respect does Swift fall short of the dynamic features of Objective-C&amp;rdquo;?
Dynamic programming means a lot of different things to different people, and I think they meant runtime programming. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at replacing Objective-C&amp;rsquo;s runtime programming with Swift&amp;rsquo;s functions.
This post is an excerpt from the Functions chapter in Advanced Swift, which we&amp;rsquo;re currently rewriting (and making very good progress).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structs and mutation in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/structs-and-mutation-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/structs-and-mutation-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>Note: This post is a draft-version of a new section in our book Advanced Swift. We&amp;rsquo;re currently updating the book for Swift 3. It&amp;rsquo;ll be a free update for everyone who has bought a digital version of the book. Thanks to Ole Begemann for suggestions and improvements.
Value types imply that whenever a variable is copied, the value itself — and not just a reference to the value — is copied.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protocols in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/protocols-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/protocols-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s say we are writing our own data-structure, a singly linked list:
enum ListNode&amp;lt;A&amp;gt; { case end indirect case cons(A, ListNode) }  Today&amp;rsquo;s goal is to make ListNode conform to the Collection protocol. It&amp;rsquo;s actually fairly easy, but it&amp;rsquo;s almost impossible to figure it out by just looking at the types. The documentation tells us which methods to implement, but why is it like that? Even though the protocol is clearly specified, it&amp;rsquo;s not so easy to see what you need to do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Responder Chain Alternatives</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/responder-chain-alternative/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/responder-chain-alternative/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s been some recent talk about the responder chain. The responder chain works on a tree structure: the view hierarchy plus some other things. An event or action gets sent to a certain view (a node in the tree structure). Until it gets handled, it moves up the tree towards the root, going through all superviews, all the way until the NSWindow, up to the NSWindowController. You can even modify this tree structure, and insert your own responders.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Undo History in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/undo-history-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/undo-history-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>Over the last weeks, there have been a number of blog posts that want to add dynamic behavior to Swift. Swift is already a very dynamic language: it has generics, protocols, first-class functions, and the standard library is filled with functions like map and filter, which dynamically get their operation (not using a string like with KVC, but using a function, which is safer and more flexible). Most of the people that say they want dynamic behavior mean that they want reflection specifically: they want to analyze and modify the program at runtime.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/dynamic-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/dynamic-swift/</guid>
      <description>Recently, Brent and others wrote a lot about the lack of dynamic features1 in Swift. I tried distilling Brent&amp;rsquo;s thoughts, and came up with the following summary:
 It&amp;rsquo;s easy to write code in AppKit and UIKit, because many things just work, without having to write a lot of code. AppKit/UIKit are written in Objective-C, and use runtime programming to remove boilerplate. Therefore, we either need these same features in Swift, or need to find a different way of solving some problems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rejected Swift Proposals</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/rejected-swift-proposals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2016 15:46:42 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/rejected-swift-proposals/</guid>
      <description>Not too long ago, we finally shipped Advanced Swift. It was a long process, but I&amp;rsquo;m really happy about the result. Just before we finished it, Swift became open-source, the mailing lists opened up, and many GitHub repositories appeared.
At first, I subscribed to all the mailing lists, and added a filter to move them into a separate folder. There was so much discussion that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t keep up at all - at least not while finishing the book.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Struct Semantics in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/struct-semantics-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/struct-semantics-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>In our book Advanced Swift, we show how to implement your own copy-on-write structs in detail. This blogpost shows the same technique, but in less detail.
One big difference between Swift strings and Cocoa strings is how they deal with mutability. If you define a Swift string using let, the compiler enforces immutability: there is no way to change the string:
let myString = &amp;quot;immutable string&amp;quot; myString += &amp;quot; test&amp;quot; // Illegal  In Cocoa, the same is done using classes: an NSString is immutable, and an NSMutableString is mutable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Literate Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/literate-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/literate-swift/</guid>
      <description>Last year, when we started writing Functional Programming in Swift, we realized that the language would change every few weeks. We didn&amp;rsquo;t anticipate the pace, but we were ready for change. Rather than manually updating every article, we used a technique called literate programming. In literate programming, you write the code and text at the same time. The code in the text can be executed. To do this, we wrote a small utility called Literate Swift.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swift and C functions</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-c-interop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-c-interop/</guid>
      <description>One of Swift&amp;rsquo;s greatest strengths is the low friction when interoperating with C and Objective-C. Swift can automatically bridge Objective-C types, and can even bridge with many C types. This allows us to use existing libraries, and provide a nice interface on top. In our book Advanced Swift, we will write a wrapper around cmark, and a wrapper around libuv. This post is an excerpt from a first draft of one of the C interop chapters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/advanced-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/advanced-swift/</guid>
      <description>Over the last months, Airspeed Velocity and me have been very busy writing a new book: Advanced Swift. We are quite far along, most of the book has been written already. During the next months, we will polish the chapters and release them one by one. We aim to have the book done by this fall (hopefully so we can coincide with the official Swift release).
Writing this book has been a lot of fun, and a huge learning experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Via Alpina</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/via-alpina/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/via-alpina/</guid>
      <description>In a few days, I&amp;rsquo;ll head over to Innsbruck to meet up with some friends for the weekend. After that, I&amp;rsquo;m going to start a big running adventure. My plan is to run solo across the Alps for a month, from mountain hut to mountain hut. I&amp;rsquo;ll be bringing a small backpack, filled mostly with warm layers and my laptop. In the mornings, I plan to run, and in the afternoons, I&amp;rsquo;ll write my new book.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swift Mirrors and JSON</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-mirrors-and-json/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-mirrors-and-json/</guid>
      <description>Inspired by Mike Ash&amp;rsquo;s tweet, I tried generating JSON dictionaries in Swift by using the new reflection features. First of all, let&amp;rsquo;s create two structs for holding a person and an address:
struct Address { var street: String } struct Person { var name: String = &amp;quot;John&amp;quot; var age: Int = 42 var dutch: Bool = false var address: Address? = Address(street: &amp;quot;Market St.&amp;quot;) } let john = Person()  We can introspect values using the reflect function.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monads in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/monads-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/monads-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>Last year, many people have dipped their toes into functional programming. Unfortunately, one of the side-effects of learning functional programming is a great amount of people trying to explain monads. Many explanations I&amp;rsquo;ve seen were bad and only add to the existing confusion. This makes me quite upset sometimes.
So here&amp;rsquo;s my very short (and slightly simplified) explanation:
 If you can define flatMap for a type, the type is often called a monad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Race Report: Rotterdam Marathon</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/race-report-rotterdam-harzquerung/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/race-report-rotterdam-harzquerung/</guid>
      <description>After my first marathon, I wanted to do a better job at running my next marathon. Instead of training by myself, I decided to work with Mark, who made a training plan for me leading up to the Rotterdam Marathon. I spent a few months in New York, a while in San Francisco, and generally traveled around while still putting in my training, this went surprisingly well. I even ran some races in the US (and won a 5K in Brooklyn).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swift in Production: Scenery</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/scenery-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/scenery-launch/</guid>
      <description>Today, we shipped our first Swift app completely written in Swift: Scenery. From our press release:
 Scenery is the Mac app that makes your app or website designs look instantly beautiful and professional, by putting them in context – placed into smartphones, tablets, laptops, and more – in stunningly-photographed scenes.
 It&amp;rsquo;s been a very interesting experience, because all iOS and Mac apps we&amp;rsquo;ve built before were done using Objective-C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Boring Choice</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/boring-choice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/boring-choice/</guid>
      <description>I love new and experimental technologies. These days, I like trying to push Swift to the limits. I once wrote a Haskell web backend for financial transactions that used lots of generic programming. When Rails was just out, I started playing around with it (back when hosting was really complicated, except if you wanted PHP3 and MySQL). I&amp;rsquo;ve used all these things in production code, mainly in very small teams.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional View Controllers</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/functional-view-controllers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/functional-view-controllers/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m working on something new: a functional wrapper around view controllers. Making view controllers simpler has been a long obsession for me. I think functional view controllers might make them even simpler. This is still very much work in progress, but I hope that over the next months I can flesh out something nice. For this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll work with artists and albums, and this is how they&amp;rsquo;re defined:
struct Album { let name: String } struct Artist { let name : String let albums: [Album] }  And here&amp;rsquo;s some example data:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repmin in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/repmin-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/repmin-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>This might be my most obscure functional programming post yet.
Yesterday, I attended the Dutch Functional Programming Day, and it was very nice to see many old friends. Doaitse&amp;rsquo;s talk was about different solutions to the repmin problem (and related problems). Repmin is a slightly obscure problem (but famous amoung a small group of functional programmers):
Given a binary tree with integers at the leaves, replace each leave&amp;rsquo;s value by the minimum value in the tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/2014/</guid>
      <description>Continuing from my 2013 retrospective, here&amp;rsquo;s one for 2014.
In the beginning of the year, Florian and me moved into the A Color Bright office (which has been awesome). We continued working on Deckset, and launched Deckset in April. It&amp;rsquo;s been a really rewarding experience to have a product out, maintain it and have lots of happy users. We have some great plans for next year.
In May, we organized the second edition of UIKonf.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Burnout: five years later</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/burnout-five-years-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/burnout-five-years-later/</guid>
      <description>About five years ago, I had a burnout. Or at least, something very similar to it. I had no joy programming anymore, especially programming for iOS. I wrote some stream-of-consciousness posts about it. Now, five years later, I&amp;rsquo;m a very happy programmer again. I&amp;rsquo;m writing this to figure out what happened in between.
When I realized things weren&amp;rsquo;t going to well with me, the first thing that I did is taking a few months off.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CocoaConf</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/cocoaconf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/cocoaconf/</guid>
      <description>This summer, I was in touch with CocoaConf about speaking at their Boston edition. After they checked their schedules, they confirmed me as a speaker, and asked me if I could swing a second talk so that they could cover my flight from NY and my hotel. I&amp;rsquo;ve never given two talks at a single conference, but I was happy to do it: challenge accepted. I started organizing my flight to the US around this, I had started planning my two talks, and got super excited about meeting all these awesome people.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lenses in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lenses-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lenses-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>This is another FP-inspired blogpost, this time about lenses. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of literature around lenses, but I wanted to show some simple examples.
Sometimes, you have a set of data (this could be anything, from a struct to a Core Data database, or a webservice), and you want to create a view on that data. For example, suppose you have a value of type Person, you might want to create a view that only has a specific person&amp;rsquo;s address.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tiny networking library</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/tiny-networking-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/tiny-networking-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>For a new project we&amp;rsquo;ve been working on at Unsigned Integer, the company behind Deckset, we needed to wrap a webservice API. I had a look at both Alamofire and Moya. Alamofire is a full-featured networking library, and if I would need something with more features, I would almost certainly use it. Moya is also very nice, and is built on top of Alomofire, and provides some extra safety. However, neither of them provide a simple way to parse results, so I started to experiment a bit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Race Report: Munich Marathon</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/race-report-munich-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/race-report-munich-marathon/</guid>
      <description>Today, I want to write about non-code: yesterday I ran my first real marathon. Although I did run the distance before, never in a road race. Another runner I met once said:
 One of the best things you can do for your body, is train for a marathon. One of the worst things you can do is to actually run it.
 I couldn&amp;rsquo;t agree more. I&amp;rsquo;ve been feeling really good after all the training, however, today, the day after the marathon, my body is not so happy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuples, Structs and Enums</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/tuples-structs-enums/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/tuples-structs-enums/</guid>
      <description>Swift has lots of different ways of storing your data. You can use enums, tuples, structs, classes (or even just use malloc and manage it yourself)! In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll compare enums, tuples and structs. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the simplest: tuples.
A tuple is a typed list of values. For example, you can define a tuple that holds an integer and a string:
let amount = (100, &amp;quot;EUR&amp;quot;)  This is very useful when you want to return multiple values from a function.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some ideas for projects in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-ideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-ideas/</guid>
      <description>If you are looking for some programming projects to port to Swift, my list is way bigger than I can tackle. Most ideas here are ports of libraries from other languages, some are different. I would love to build all of these, but can&amp;rsquo;t possibly do even ten percent of this list. The list is in random order.
 An SVG Parser that can parse SVG, turn it into an abstract syntax tree, and has support to render it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Type-safe URL routes in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/typesafe-url-routes-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/typesafe-url-routes-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>While Ash Furrow is working on his Moya project, I got inspired by his approach, and decided to write a little bit of code to demonstrate a technique I used in Haskell a few years ago.
It uses Swift enums to describe API endpoints. Instead of describing endpoints this with strings, you can use Swift&amp;rsquo;s enums to make it type-safe and well-documented. Let&amp;rsquo;s build an example that wraps a very small part of the GitHub API.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Blub Paradox in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/blub-paradox-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/blub-paradox-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>In his article Beating the Averages, Paul Graham writes about the Blub paradox. I think this is excellent reading for every programmer, the article is full of interesting advice.
The Blub paradox is about a hypothetical language Blub, but in this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll talk about Objective-C. Objective-C is a major improvement over C in terms of productivity. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know how I would get anything done in C, coming from Objective-C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parsing JSON in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/json-parsing-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/json-parsing-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>headline: Safe and easy
After reading Brent&amp;rsquo;s and David&amp;rsquo;s posts on parsing JSON in Swift, I really wanted to write this post. However, we&amp;rsquo;ve been very busy with writing a book on Functional Programming in Swift, and I wanted to finish some other things first, so it took a while to come up with it. The full code accompanying this post is on GitHub.
In this posts I will give an outline of a parsing library for dealing with JSON in Swift in a type-safe way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Programming in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/functional-programming-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/functional-programming-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, after Apple announced their new programming language Swift, it became very clear to me that we had to write a book on Functional Programming in Swift. Once the idea was there, I just couldn&amp;rsquo;t stop thinking about it anymore. After getting Wouter and Florian on board, I knew we had a killer team for writing this book.
We decided to do give people early access, so they can read along and comment as we proceed with the writing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swift Tricks</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-tricks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/swift-tricks/</guid>
      <description>Here are some quick Swift functions that can make your life easier. First, a function that splits up an array into head and tail:
extension Array { var match : (head: T, tail: [T])? { return (count &amp;gt; 0) ? (self[0],Array(self[1..&amp;lt;count])) : nil } }  You can use it like this:
func map&amp;lt;A,B&amp;gt;(f: A -&amp;gt; B, arr: [A]) -&amp;gt; [B] { if let (head,tail) = arr.match { return [f(head)] + map(f, tail) } else { return [] } }  If you lazily want to generate a list of things, but don&amp;rsquo;t really know how many will be needed, you can use a Generator.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QuickCheck in Swift</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/quickcheck-in-swift/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/quickcheck-in-swift/</guid>
      <description>This afternoon, I&amp;rsquo;ve been making my first steps in Swift, trying to see how much of my Haskell knowledge I could port. It seems like a lot of cool stuff you can do with types is not yet possible, I already filed some radars.
As an experiment, this article is also available as a playground and on github. Because we&amp;rsquo;ll need the arc4random function, we&amp;rsquo;ll start by importing Foundation:
import Foundation  I wanted to see if it&amp;rsquo;s possible to implement something like QuickCheck in Swift.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intentions</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/intentions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/intentions/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of lighter view controllers. In the first issue of objc.io, I wrote an article about it. Since then, I&amp;rsquo;ve given a couple of talks about it. Most of the things you can do are very straightforward once you know them, and people seem to generally like it. However, a couple of months ago, I read a great blogpost explaining how to take the notion of &amp;lsquo;lighter view controllers&amp;rsquo; up a notch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We launched Deckset</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/we-launched-deckset/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/we-launched-deckset/</guid>
      <description>I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be more proud to share with you that we launched Deckset yesterday. There are a lot of nice stories to tell about how we worked as a team, why it took us 5 times longer than expected to build this, and how we finally shipped. There are so many interesting technical details to share. However, today I won&amp;rsquo;t talk about the process, but why I am so proud of the result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fast Running</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/fast-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/fast-running/</guid>
      <description>When I&amp;rsquo;m not working, a lot of my time and energy is spent running. Last year, in preparation for the Berlin Marathon, I was running 4-5 times a week, and also doing strength training 1-2 times a week. Last year, in April, I also ran a PB on the 10K: 37:03. Compared to average runners, this is quite fast (however, in almost every race there are people who are a lot faster).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working for the man</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/working-for-the-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/working-for-the-man/</guid>
      <description>I got my first programming job when I was 16. I had made a website for the local library, and one of the two computer companies in the village had gotten my contact details. I went there, and started building a CMS in PHP for him. I was 15 or 16 years old, and loved it. I built and designed a lot of websites for all the local companies (the plumber, the party-rental-service, the truck company, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding designers</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/finding-designers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/finding-designers/</guid>
      <description>When Florian and me started working on Deckset, we realized we needed the best possible design. In every app, great design is important, but here, it&amp;rsquo;s even more important: we will provide users with themes that have to look really great by default.
When we started looking for designers, there were a couple of people that came to mind, because we&amp;rsquo;ve worked with them before. However, with the two most serious candidates, we&amp;rsquo;ve had a couple of issues: even though we love what they made, the process of working with them before was not too nice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behind the scenes</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-write-for-objcio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-write-for-objcio/</guid>
      <description>headline: How I write my articles for objc.io
My workflow for writing an objc.io article is like this:
Once we release an issue, we often have the topic for the next issue ready. Florian, Daniel and me get together and we discuss and try to distribute the relevant topics among the three of us (in addition to the guest articles that are already planned). For example, for the strings issue, I knew my topic would be string parsing, and that I would talk about scanners, regular expressions and parsers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deckset</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/deckset/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/deckset/</guid>
      <description>One of the things I love is Markdown. Recently, I&amp;#8217;ve also been giving a lot more presentations. Working in Keynote can be really nice, and is very powerful. But most of the time, I don&amp;#8217;t need that power.
Therefore, Florian, me and our awesome friends at A Color Bright have spent the last months building an app that changes the way you write your presentations. You write a markdown file, separate your slides with dashes, and you get a beautiful presentation out of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2013</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/2013/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#8217;s the time of the year to write a recap about the things I&amp;#8217;ve done this year. 2013 has been a really awesome year, maybe my best year so far. I learned tons, worked with really awesome people, made many new friends and travelled a lot.
Client work This year, I worked for three big clients (and some smaller ones). The smallest of three was an old employer who wanted a prototype of a new idea (in Ruby on Rails).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lightweight Key-Value Observing</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lightweight-key-value-observing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lightweight-key-value-observing/</guid>
      <description>In this article, I&amp;#8217;d like to implement a simple class I use for key-value observing. I think KVO is great, however, for most of what I do, there are two problems:
I don&amp;#8217;t like the dispatching in observeValueForKeyPath:ofObject:change:context:. I think it gets messy and confusing if you observe more than one object. You have to balance each add observer with a remove observer, it would be nice if this can be done automatically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status Update</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/status-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/status-update/</guid>
      <description>Lots of stuff happened over the last months, so here&amp;#8217;s a partial list:
I finished my project with Aprendo. We&amp;#8217;ve been working on an in-house iPad app for almost a year. At this point, I can&amp;#8217;t demo anything publicly, but I&amp;#8217;d be happy to talk about it in private. I organized UIKonf together with Peter and Matt. I think it&amp;#8217;s safe to say that the conference was a resounding success. We learned a lot of things that we can do better next year, but all in all, we&amp;#8217;re very happy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DONE</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/done/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/done/</guid>
      <description>In case you haven&amp;#8217;t noticed yet, I&amp;#8217;m organizing an English-speaking iOS Conference in Berlin called UIKonf, together with my fellow organizers Matt and Peter. If you are in or around Berlin on May 2nd, get on the mailing list and come join us!
Organizing this conference is really awesome. It started with a question: why doesn&amp;#8217;t this conference exist? Then I realized that the only way to make it happen is do it yourself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to keep your classes small and clean</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-to-keep-your-classes-small-and-clean/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-to-keep-your-classes-small-and-clean/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#8217;m a little obsessed with trying to write maintainable, clean code. I&amp;#8217;m not yet really good at it, but try to become better every day. It started to become more of an obsession than usual when I realized that a lot of the projects I work on will someday be taken over by other people, and I don&amp;#8217;t want to be embarassed.
This explains my recent interest in testing (some interesting blogs on that).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Things</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/new-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/new-things/</guid>
      <description>Over Christmas, I read Antifragile by Taleb. The book has had quite an impact on me, and I decided to change some things. Long story short: I want to be open to positive black swans. A positive black swan is an event that will happen with a low probability, but if it does happen, it has a big impact.
Taleb&amp;#8217;s strategy for investing is to invest mostly in very safe things, and make small bets with a limited downside, but an unlimited upside.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lighter UIViewControllers</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lighter-uiviewcontrollers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lighter-uiviewcontrollers/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I&amp;#8217;ve been a bit obsessed with writing simpler code. It happened because I passed on some projects to other programmers. I would like to feel minimally embarrassed when doing so.
In the projects I&amp;#8217;ve taken over from other people, one of the most common problems is that view controller code is big and complicated. In this article, we&amp;#8217;ll look at some ways to make the view controller smaller and thus simpler.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing Value Objects in Objective C</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/implementing-value-objects-in-objective-c/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/implementing-value-objects-in-objective-c/</guid>
      <description>Value Objects are objects that hold simple data. This article is about creating such value objects. I use them a lot in my code, because they are robust and keep the code simple. Note that it&amp;#8217;s not about NSValue, but about simple objects with simple data.
Implementing value objects should be easy, but there are some slightly tricky bits. So let&amp;#8217;s look at the requirements:
We want to create value objects quickly (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to add a new Unit Test target and OCMock to an existing XCode project</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-to-add-a-new-unit-test-target-and-ocmock-to-an/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-to-add-a-new-unit-test-target-and-ocmock-to-an/</guid>
      <description>I had some trouble today trying to add Unit Tests to an existing project that uses CocoaPods. So I decided to do a quick writeup of how I got it working:
Create a new project called &amp;#8216;BetterTodoList&amp;#8217;
 Create a new Podfile with the following contents
 platform :ios, 6.0 pod &#39;AFNetworking&#39; Close BetterTodoList in XCode, and open the workspace (as instructed by CocoaPods)
 Run, and see that everything still works</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My presentation at the Berlin HUG</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/my-presentation-at-the-berlin-hug/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/my-presentation-at-the-berlin-hug/</guid>
      <description>Last week I gave a short presentation about lenses and fclabels at the Berlin Haskell Users Group. The source for the slides and some accompanying literate Haskell files are now in a github repo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adding push notifications to an app</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/adding-push-notifications-to-an-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/adding-push-notifications-to-an-app/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I&amp;#8217;ve built an app that&amp;#8217;s quite simple: there are categories, and in the categories are messages. People can subscribe to a category and get a push notification when there&amp;#8217;s a new message in the category, or when a significant change was made to the message. The badge icon should update appropriately, showing the number of unread messages. There are lots of tricky things when implementing this, and the point of this article is to explore them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More Interface Builder</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/more-interface-builder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/more-interface-builder/</guid>
      <description>When I started iPhone programming, I built most of my interfaces in code. It was much easier: full control over your interface. Sometimes I would start in Interface Builder, but once I stumbled upon limitations I would rewrite the whole thing in code.
After learning some more things about Interface Builder, I started using it more and more. These days, I try to do almost every UI in Interface Builder. Apple has made it a lot easier for us, too: designing your table view cells in Interface Builder was quite easy already, but is even easier with Storyboards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Traveling alone</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/traveling-alone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/traveling-alone/</guid>
      <description>I like traveling alone. Here are some things I found out when traveling alone:
Eating alone in restaurants is fine. I used to really dislike it, because I felt stared at. It got on my nerves. Once I went for mexican food in a Denver restaurant on the tech campus, and on Saturday night the restaurant was filled with families. I was seated in the middle of the room, and had a really big table just for me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding My Most Influential Twitter Followers</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/finding-my-most-influential-twitter-followers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/finding-my-most-influential-twitter-followers/</guid>
      <description>I spent an afternoon trying to find out who of my Twitter followers is the most influential. I wrote the script to fetch the data in Ruby, and stored the data in MongoDB.
Setup
First, we&amp;#8217;ll need to set up some things. Make sure you have a recent version of Ruby installed, and install the following gems:
gem install twitter mongo bson_ext  Although the bson_ext isn&amp;#8217;t really necessary, it will make things a bit faster.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing Tech Education</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/changing-tech-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/changing-tech-education/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes I talk to my friends about why I want to become rich. It&amp;#8217;s to solve the money problem, and once it&amp;#8217;s solved, I hope to have the time, connections and status to work on bigger problems. I already know exactly what I want to try once I&amp;#8217;m there: change tech education.
When I did my bachelor&amp;#8217;s degree in computer science, I was quite bored most of the time. Officially, you were supposed to work on it at least 40 hours per week, but for me and most of my friends it was closer to 10 hours.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radical Friendship</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/radical-friendship/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/radical-friendship/</guid>
      <description>A few months ago I wrote about radical honesty. I tried being more honest, but in practice it&amp;#8217;s quite awkward. Our society isn&amp;#8217;t really used to being completely honest and open. For example, if a friend wears something I really dislike, I won&amp;#8217;t tell him. It&amp;#8217;s just my opinion, and by expressing it I don&amp;#8217;t think I&amp;#8217;ll help anybody.
In How To Win Friends and Influence People, Dale Carnegie says things like &amp;#8221; &amp;#8220;Don&amp;#8217;t criticize, condemn or complain&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;The only way to get the best of an argument is to avoid it&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;Show respect for the other person&amp;#8217;s opinions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting new projects</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/starting-new-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/starting-new-projects/</guid>
      <description>One of the most exciting things for me is starting new projects. Each time I start to build a new app, I get way too excited and see rainbows and ponies everywhere. &amp;#8220;This time it&amp;#8217;s going to beautiful, easy, quick to finish and lots of fun&amp;#8221;. There is a blank slate and in my mind everything fits together perfectly.
However, in reality, after I&amp;#8217;ve spent some time on a project, I start to see the design mistakes I made.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Berlin Tech Meetups</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/berlin-tech-meetups/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/berlin-tech-meetups/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#8217;m trying to come up with a list of tech-related meetups in Berlin. This list is far from complete: please help me to add more meetups, and improve the descriptions. Just send me an email with corrections and/or suggestions. A next step would be to create a Google Calendar just like Peter Robinett did for Dutch Tech Meetups.
For people who don&amp;#8217;t speak German: Germans are very friendly and speak English, especially the techies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entitled</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/entitled/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/entitled/</guid>
      <description>This post is inspired by Marco&amp;#8217;s excellent piece: Right versus pragmatic.
I grew up in a small village. When I was 13, I didn&amp;#8217;t really have money to buy music, but I still saved up and went to the record store so I could buy Americana. When I was 15, I got my first computer-job (as a php programmer). One month, I even made 1000 guilders (which was a lot for me).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing an API using CoreData&#39;s NSIncrementalStore</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/accessing-an-api-using-coredatas-nsincrementalstore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/accessing-an-api-using-coredatas-nsincrementalstore/</guid>
      <description>{% extends &#34;post.html&#34; %} Note: I&amp;#8217;ve also posted this article on github as gist, for better readability of the code: nsincrementalstore.markdown.
In this article, we will see how to use Core Data for accessing your API. We will use the Bandcamp API as our running example. I&amp;#8217;ve only been experimenting with this code for a few days, so there might be mistakes in there.
One of the problems with accessing an API is that you typically have API calls everywhere in your code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Use This</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/i-use-this/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/i-use-this/</guid>
      <description>I was inspired by people writing about their setup on The Setup, so I decided to write about my own setup.
Hardware
I use a Mid 2010 Macbook Pro 15&amp;#8221; with an SSD. I only switched last week, when my old hard drive was about to die. I don&amp;#8217;t use any external screen, keyboard or mouse. Because I travel a lot and work from pretty much everywhere, the HD display is really convenient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Becoming a better programmer: Test-Driven Development</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/becoming-a-better-programmer-test-driven-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/becoming-a-better-programmer-test-driven-development/</guid>
      <description>As I&amp;#8217;m enjoying programming again (and more so every week), I started to think consciously again about improving myself as a programmer. After a recommendation of breun I started reading Clean Code, which I can definitely recommend.
One of the things I have always felt bad about professionally is not doing Test-Driven Development. Back when I was programming Haskell a lot I did do a lot of type-driven development, which overlaps a bit: you write down your types and then try to implement it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I write my code</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-write-my-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-write-my-code/</guid>
      <description>Recently I saw a couple of posts on how people write their code. I found it inspiring, and part of the reason I&amp;#8217;m writing this article is that I don&amp;#8217;t know how I write my code (not explicitly, at least).
Most of the time, I know what I&amp;#8217;m going to build a few days, weeks or even months beforehand. During the time between idea and building, I think about it. I don&amp;#8217;t set apart time to do that, it just happens.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Take the money</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/take-the-money/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/take-the-money/</guid>
      <description>After yesterday&amp;#8217;s post about speaking up, I got some questions about what my responsibility is as a freelance programmer. Am I qualified to judge other people&amp;#8217;s business ideas? And if so, should I tell them if it&amp;#8217;s a bad idea? I&amp;#8217;m a computer programmer, maybe I should just stick to what I know.
The question I&amp;#8217;m trying to answer is: &amp;#8220;Should I just take the money?&amp;#8221;
I&amp;#8217;m not sure if it is my responsibility to judge other people&amp;#8217;s business ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking Up</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/speaking-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/speaking-up/</guid>
      <description>Deciding when to speak up is one of the things where I feel I haven&amp;#8217;t yet figured it out at all. I don&amp;#8217;t know when or how to do it.
In high school, a friend of mine didn&amp;#8217;t like her boyfriend anymore. I told her that if she really feels that way then she should break up with him. The boyfriend (who was a good friend of me as well) was, understandably, quite angry at me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Focus</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/focus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/focus/</guid>
      <description>When people tell me their startup idea, it often happens that they are trying to solve a huge amount of problems. This happens mostly with people who do not have a lot of experience in startups. These people are often very ambitious but don&amp;#8217;t have the skills to execute themselves.
For me, focus has always worked in business. The first company I started, we didn&amp;#8217;t really know what to do, so we told people we could program everything.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Willpower</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/willpower/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/willpower/</guid>
      <description>I hate flossing. My dentist insists that I do it, and after each visit I promised to do better next time, but never followed through. I wanted to, but I lacked the discipline to do it.
Some two months ago, I decided to do it differently. Instead of using my willpower, I tricked myself into creating a habit. I grabbed a big piece of paper, made rows and columns, creating about 60 large squares.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freeform blogging</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/freeform-blogging/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/freeform-blogging/</guid>
      <description>In the last days, I tried to do more freeform blogging. I&amp;#8217;ll write about whatever&amp;#8217;s on my mind. Some pieces might be about something I&amp;#8217;ve been thinking about for months, others might be something I just thought of in the shower.
I will try not to care too much about things like &amp;#8216;target audience&amp;#8217;. My goal is to become better at writing and to help myself think. I&amp;#8217;ll try to write again every day, and publish it regardless of whether it&amp;#8217;s good or bad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My perfect co-founder</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/my-perfect-co-founder/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/my-perfect-co-founder/</guid>
      <description>Being a programmer, I have long thought about my ideal co-founder. I&amp;#8217;ve started a company with somebody who&amp;#8217;s got almost the same skillset as I have (except that he could do bookkeeping as well). This worked for two years, but I didn&amp;#8217;t like the direction we were going in. After that, I started a startup with a mathematician, analyzing big data. Here, we couldn&amp;#8217;t agree upon the product, and weren&amp;#8217;t to good at selling ourselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Breakups</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/on-breakups/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/on-breakups/</guid>
      <description>Not too long ago, I went through a breakup, or to put it another way: I got dumped. Fortunately, this wasn&amp;#8217;t the first time I went through a breakup. Everybody handles it differently, but these are the sort of things that help me deal with it:
I meet a lot of friends and talk about it. I go out to bars where nice girls hang out, just to reassure myself that there are more girls out there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radical Honesty</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/radical-honesty/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/radical-honesty/</guid>
      <description>On Hacker News, I read an article about Radical Honesty today: I Think You&amp;#8217;re Fat. It really appealed to me. Over the last year, I&amp;#8217;ve tried to be more open and honest myself. Not radically honest, though. For me, it was important not to hurt other people&amp;#8217;s feelings.
However, when you think of it, you can hurt people more by not being honest. Suppose a friend lets you wait for 45 minutes in a restaurant.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CocoaPods</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/cocoapods/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/cocoapods/</guid>
      <description>I just upgraded one of my projects to use CocoaPods. CocoaPods is a library dependency manager for XCode projects. You can use it in a way similar to Ruby&amp;#8217;s gems or Haskell&amp;#8217;s cabal. The project is just starting, so it&amp;#8217;s a little rough, but it does the job.
I think this can make code sharing for iOS developers a lot easier. I&amp;#8217;m all for reusing code, but it used to be quite a hassle to include a library, so a lot of times I would try to avoid reusing other code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hard Decisions</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/hard-decisions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/hard-decisions/</guid>
      <description>Over the last few weeks, I was asked three times (by two different companies) to become the development lead (i.e. CTO). Both of these companies are really quite awesome, and I can see them become very succesful (actually, one already is quite succesful). I strongly considerd saying yes to both positions, but ultimately decided not to do it.
One of the companies already makes good profits, the other one is just starting but can become very profitable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Satisficers vs. Optimizers</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/satisficers-vs-optimizers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/satisficers-vs-optimizers/</guid>
      <description>I just finished Fooled by Randomness by Taleb, what a great book. In the last chapter, he compares satisficers and optimizers: suppose you&amp;#8217;re having dinner with a friend who knows exactly when his train leaves. He optimizes his dinner, hurrying away from the table just before his train is about to depart. Your friend is an optimizer.
I am aspiring to be more of a satisficer: I don&amp;#8217;t know when my train will leave.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Survivorship bias</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/survivorship-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/survivorship-bias/</guid>
      <description>Of all the jobs I&amp;#8217;ve had, being a solo entrepreneur is the fairest job. I am directly responsible for my own income. I have nobody to blame if things go wrong, technically, financially or otherwise. This makes me feel very responsible for everything I do. Compared to working with more than one person or (worse) working in a company, my work influences my results so much more.
The danger is this: if I become very successful, I will probably attribute it to my skill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Running</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/on-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/on-running/</guid>
      <description>Running gives me a lot of energy. After a run, there is the runner&amp;#8217;s high: the released endorphin in my brain makes me feel great.
Training, races and continually wanting to get better makes me push myself. I&amp;#8217;m not pushing too much, for risk of over-training, but I am constantly overcoming barriers and improving. After running my first half marathon a few years ago, I felt on top of the world, and that feeling lasted an entire week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Met has launched</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/met-has-launched/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/met-has-launched/</guid>
      <description>Today is the official release of Met. I will send out a press release to all the Dutch iOS websites, and will send out an press release in English tomorrow. The last few weeks have been quite an adventure. I documented all the steps of building Met on this weblog, starting with choosing an idea and ending with submitting it to the App Store.
For those that haven&amp;#8217;t read the story yet: Met is an application that allows you to take notes on people.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HTML5 is no silver bullet for apps</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/html5-is-no-silver-bullet-for-apps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/html5-is-no-silver-bullet-for-apps/</guid>
      <description>I sometimes hear people tell me that they are going to let their next app be an HTML 5 app. This way, they can write for both iPhone and Android at the same time. This seems like a big win.
Although iOS and Android are very similar, both being touch-based and mobile, they are also quite different. For example:
On Android, if you want to go back to the screen you just came from, you press the physical &amp;#8216;Back&amp;#8217; button on the device.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reaching a plateau</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/reaching-a-plateau/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/reaching-a-plateau/</guid>
      <description>While I was traveling last month, I met a lot of great people. One of them was a 73-year old woman who had been very successful in her life. She was a professor at a well-known university in the USA and has now retired to Spain. She is still doing amazing things.
I asked her: &amp;#8220;What&amp;#8217;s your secret to success, apart from working hard and being intelligent?&amp;#8221;. She said: &amp;#8220;Nothing, just that&amp;#8221;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Met In The App Store</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/met-in-the-app-store/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/met-in-the-app-store/</guid>
      <description>This morning at 10:11 GMT+1, version 1.0 of Met was submitted to the App Store. It&amp;#8217;s been quite an experience, blogging about everything, from before there was an idea until the App Store submission. I will write a recap of everything next week.
In the last few days, I&amp;#8217;ve been helping out with an ultra marathon, and met a lot of interesting and inspiring people. There was a 73-year old guy who ran 160 kilometers (100 miles) who finished without any problems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New build, first website, press plans</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/new-build-first-website-press-plans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/new-build-first-website-press-plans/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I released a new build. In this version, you can also change the date of events (which means you can add past events) and add new contacts from within the app.
Today I set up a first webpage for Met. I really like the design of With, and I let myself be inspired. Admittedly, the website is quite minimal, but I think it should be enough (for now). I also found a good domain name, which I&amp;#8217;m in the process of registering now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I Will Design My App Website</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-will-design-my-app-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-will-design-my-app-website/</guid>
      <description>For Met, I need to design and build a website, and in this post I&amp;#8217;ll show some of best the app websites I&amp;#8217;ve bookmarked and try to explain why I like them. My definition of &amp;#8220;best&amp;#8221; in this case mostly means beautiful. I don&amp;#8217;t know how they convert visitors or any other performance, so that&amp;#8217;s something I need to measure myself.
Screenshots
Perhaps the most important part of an app website are the screenshots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3: An App in Four Weeks</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/week-3-an-app-in-four-weeks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/week-3-an-app-in-four-weeks/</guid>
      <description>Today marks the end of Week 3 of my App in Four Weeks challenge.
This week I chose a name. I designed an icon and overall style for the app. I then spent quite some time implementing autorotation, and getting it exactly right. There is now a passcode lock too.
By nature, I am not a perfectionist. Whenever I see that something works, I tend to lose interest in finishing it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New build and screenshots</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/new-build-and-screenshots/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/new-build-and-screenshots/</guid>
      <description>A new build should arrive in the inbox of the beta testers right about now. It&amp;#8217;s almost the same as described yesterday, except with less bugs. My energy is a bit low today, so instead of text, here are some screenshots of the current state of the app.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rotation fun</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/rotation-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/rotation-fun/</guid>
      <description>Today I spent a lot of time implementing landscape orientation, next to portrait orientation (as this gives you a bigger keyboard). However, in the end I managed to nail it, I think. Everything resizes, moves around and plays nice with showing and hiding the keyboard.
I also added hover effects for the passcode buttons, designed the section header, changed the passcode screen slightly, added swipe to delete and changed the selection color of the text.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Met</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/introducing-met/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/introducing-met/</guid>
      <description>After yesterday&amp;#8217;s post, a lot of people contacted me with ideas for a name. Thanks Pim, Martijn, Miles, Wilfred and Fabian (I hope I didn&amp;#8217;t forget somebody). Some liked James, some liked Meetups, all with good reasons.
However, one reply stood out: Jurriaan had an idea for a more minimalistic name: &amp;#8220;Met&amp;#8221;. Short and to the point. It&amp;#8217;s about who you met. The best thing is: in Dutch it means &amp;#8220;with&amp;#8221;, and this is about who you were with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beta and Branding</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/beta-and-branding/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/beta-and-branding/</guid>
      <description>This is the start of week 3 of my One App in Four Weeks project. Last Friday, I sent out the first beta version, and just sent an update (with mostly bugfixes).
Martijn Reintjes suggested that I should change Checkins to Meetups, and I couldn&amp;#8217;t agree more. I wasn&amp;#8217;t happy with Checkins to start with, and this makes it a lot simpler. Thanks dude!
Because I wanted to be future-proof, I decided to change it everywhere in the code too.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iOS products are a local optimum</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/ios-products-are-a-local-optimum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/ios-products-are-a-local-optimum/</guid>
      <description>This morning, I was sitting in the booming heart of Seville, sipping my café con leche and reading The State of the Art is Terrible by Zack Morris. A great read indeed.
It then finally dawned on me: most apps are a local optimum. This includes most of the apps I&amp;#8217;ve worked on, including the most successful ones. Another fine example is the gorgeous Thermo app. Even though I love using it, it is just another way to view the weather forecast.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2: design improvements</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/week-2-design-improvements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/week-2-design-improvements/</guid>
      <description>This post is about Week 2 of my One App in Four Weeks project.
This week was a bit strange, in many ways. For me, it didn&amp;#8217;t feel like a productive week. On Monday and Tuesday I got some things done, Wednesday I was travelling (but thinking) and Thursday I spent most of the day creating a custom design in Photoshop. I then decided that it wasn&amp;#8217;t good enough. Instead, I chose to go for the default styles used in all of Apple&amp;#8217;s apps and Twitter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Steve Jobs</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/rip-steve-jobs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/rip-steve-jobs/</guid>
      <description>When I started to read the news this morning, I couldn&amp;#8217;t believe it. It felt very surreal. Not completely awake yet, I opened up other news sites to make sure it wasn&amp;#8217;t a mistake.
I&amp;#8217;m not sure how I feel. Mostly, I feel love. I am impressed by the products Apple made and the inspiration they gave everybody. If there&amp;#8217;s one company that I love, it must be Apple. And loving Apple implies loving Steve Jobs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selecting People Faster</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/selecting-people-faster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/selecting-people-faster/</guid>
      <description>Today, I fixed some minor things in the code, and simplified the workflow. In the previous version, when checking in, you were presented with a list of people. After that, you could do the checkin.
In the current version, it works much like sending an email or sms: you start by typing somebody&amp;#8217;s name, and you will see a list of people below (see the screenshot). After you click on a name, you can continue with typing the note.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Start of Week 2</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/start-of-week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/start-of-week-2/</guid>
      <description>Today is the start of the second week of the One App in Four Weeks challenge.
Last Friday, I added tabs to the application: one for the most recent checkins, and one for the list of contacts. More tabs will probably come, such as search and settings.
This week, I will try to get the functionality done. I need to add a Person view (after you press on a Person you see the history), fix some shortcuts I took, add search and add a passcode lock (as Lucas said, this is indeed a very sensitive application).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One App in Four Weeks: Week 1</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/one-app-in-four-weeks-week-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/one-app-in-four-weeks-week-1/</guid>
      <description>This Monday, I started One App in Four Weeks. I started by posting a list of ideas. The third idea was the most appealling to people (although I still want to build the other two as well, but not now), and I got some great feedback from everybody.
I selected the idea and defined the Minimum Viable Product, which is quite simple: you can check in to people, add a time and note to that checkin and possibly a location as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sketches and ideas</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/sketches-and-ideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/sketches-and-ideas/</guid>
      <description>Although I was traveling yesterday, I sketched some small mockups for the Contacts app. The idea for the app had come when the genius Lucas Tieleman explained to me how he keeps a small book with notes about everyone. Yesterday he sent an email with the notes he had about me: it&amp;#8217;s fun and only freaked me out a little bit (not as much as I expected). He&amp;#8217;s a very early adopter of new technology, and he wanted this on his iPhone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Check In to People</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/check-in-to-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/check-in-to-people/</guid>
      <description>As I wrote in yesterday&amp;#8217;s post, I&amp;#8217;m going to build an app in four weeks. Now I&amp;#8217;ve chosen the idea that I&amp;#8217;m going to build: check in to people. This will give you an archive of when you met people. After you check in, you can add notes and maybe pictures.
Yesterday I&amp;#8217;ve thought about the next steps and about the minimum viable product, and researched existing apps.
Existing Software</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One app in four weeks: kickoff</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/one-app-in-four-weeks-kickoff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/one-app-in-four-weeks-kickoff/</guid>
      <description>When I woke up this morning I heard the sound of the Mediterranean sea and saw palm trees out the window. Yesterday night I arrived in Malaga, Spain. I&amp;#8217;ll be slowly travelling around the area for the next few weeks. I probably won&amp;#8217;t be working full days, as it&amp;#8217;s very beautiful here, and there are a lot of things to see and do.
Originally, I had a nice plan for my work-related time during these weeks: build four apps in four weeks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trust your geeks</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/trust-your-geeks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/trust-your-geeks/</guid>
      <description>15 years ago, my local library had a night about &amp;#8220;The Internet&amp;#8221;. At that time, I read bits about it in a science magazine, and I was fascinated and persuaded my dad to take me there. That night, a guy came and talked to us about what the internet was, and what you could do. He sent an email to the White House, and got a reply within half an hour!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niche and Top Lists apps</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/niche-and-top-lists-apps/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/niche-and-top-lists-apps/</guid>
      <description>At yesterday&amp;#8217;s CocoaHeads meetup, I was discussing with Ben the marketing strategy for his app, Captio. It is aimed at people who want to capture their notes quickly: as soon as you open the app, it shows an input field, end when you press Send the note is emailed to yourself. It&amp;#8217;s been my favorite app for a long time.
The problem with Captio is that it is mostly useful for a niche group: people who capture their ideas a lot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TrackMe plans</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/trackme-plans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/trackme-plans/</guid>
      <description>Last month, I made € 99.54 from selling TrackMe. The first day I sold about 60 copies, and the rest of the sales was spread out over the month.
The reason why I sold so little is that I didn&amp;#8217;t do any marketing. I set up a blog for the app, and talked about it on this blog. I announced it on Twitter, and wrote a blog post about 10 cool things you can do with a GPX file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Communicate Often</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/communicate-often/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/communicate-often/</guid>
      <description>This advice is for freelancers: please communicate as often as possible. When somebody hires you, they want to know what&amp;#8217;s going on. Sometimes you get so caught up in trying to make a deadline or staying productive, and forget to communicate. For a client, this can be frustrating, because it looks like nothing happens (while you were even busier than you would normally be).
In my opinion, bad communication is one of the hardest problems in technology (and in life in general).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AirBnB for dogs</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/airbnb-for-dogs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/airbnb-for-dogs/</guid>
      <description>Are you thinking of building a new website? Or an app? AirBnB for dogs? A Groupon/Twitter/Facebook mashup? Mobile first? Sometimes it&amp;#8217;s kind of hard to see, it looks like all the good ideas are taken already, and we can only combine existing ones. It&amp;#8217;s all kinds of products. As an app developer, I sometimes think all the apps are already built.
I had a perfectly good idea two months ago: a YouTube remote, where you control YouTube from your iPhone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lost In Translation</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lost-in-translation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lost-in-translation/</guid>
      <description>One of the hardest part in software development is communication. I don&amp;#8217;t mean network communication, but person-to-person communication. This is one reason why it&amp;#8217;s so convenient to work alone on your pet projects: you don&amp;#8217;t have to communicate at all.
Every time you communicate, there is noise in the signal. Because both parties have different backgrounds, you lose part of the message whenever you talk to somebody else. In general, the more similar the backgounds (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Be Visible</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/be-visible/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/be-visible/</guid>
      <description>Whatever you are doing, make sure you&amp;#8217;re visible. Don&amp;#8217;t fear embarrassment and publish yourself, in whichever form. Here are three stories:
Twitter
As I wrote in an earlier post, I became iPhone developer by chance. Just for fun, we created a game called CookieCombo to play around with the iPhone SDK, which came out a few months earlier. We tweeted about it, and got two instant gigs out of it: we built the app for Wakoopa and the app for NRC (a leading Dutch newspaper).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crossing the chasm between design and code</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/crossing-the-chasm-between-design-and-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/crossing-the-chasm-between-design-and-code/</guid>
      <description>Recently there was an excellent post by Mike Rundle about how one person can be a designer and programmer at once.
I think having a designer and programmer in the same person is a great idea. I wish I would be better at design (not only do I lack experience, I&amp;#8217;m also not sure if I would have the patience to become a good designer).
When I&amp;#8217;ve worked with designers before, I sometimes noticed that they would just give me a design to implement, which I did.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So, you want to build an app together?</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/so-you-want-to-build-an-app-together/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/so-you-want-to-build-an-app-together/</guid>
      <description>If you do have an idea for an iPhone app, I want to ask you these questions. These should hopefully validate your idea and commitment.
Does it exist already?
Have you searched the App Store and the internet? Also for different keywords? If it does exist, how are you going to differentiate?
How will you make money with it?
Will you sell the app, or make it free? Will it be ad-based?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why people love and hate Macs</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/why-people-love-and-hate-macs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/why-people-love-and-hate-macs/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I have been reading a bit about cognitive dissonance, and I am fascinated by it. For example, this video shows a great example of cognitive dissonance: if people get paid only a little for a boring task that takes an hour, they experience dissonance, and need to justify it for themselves. They will say they like doing the task. However, if people get paid more, they don&amp;#8217;t need to justify it and will be honest about the task.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;ve got an idea for an app</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/ive-got-an-idea-for-an-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/ive-got-an-idea-for-an-app/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#8217;ve been an iPhone developer for over three years now. The first app I built was CookieCombo. We sold enough copies to go bowling twice, but still it was completely worth it. We tweeted about it, and got some awesome gigs out of that. Everybody was in need of iPhone developers, and there was a huge shortage. Good times.
As more and more people got to know that I&amp;#8217;m an iPhone developer, I got to hear the following phrase more often: &amp;#8220;Hey, you know, I got a great idea for an app&amp;#8221;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How a burnout changed my life</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-a-burnout-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-a-burnout-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>In the previous two posts, I wrote about my burnout. First about how I got it, then about how I dealt with it. I have the feeling it has changed me permanently, but mostly in a good way.
I don&amp;#8217;t work as hard anymore. I don&amp;#8217;t want to work weekends and evenings. Of course, every now and then I feel the urge to do something, but I try to resist. I read more, and take more time to socialize.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I dealt with a burnout</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-dealt-with-a-burnout/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-dealt-with-a-burnout/</guid>
      <description>This post is the second part of my series on burnout. Read the first part to know how I got there.
The first month after graduating, I spent exercising and sitting on the couch. Exercising made me feel good, especially the running pulled me through. However, still no joy in programming.
It is interesting to note that I didn&amp;#8217;t feel down all the time, it was very much work-related. Actually, most of the time I felt pretty OK.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I got a burnout</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-got-a-burnout/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-i-got-a-burnout/</guid>
      <description>This post is the first part of a three-part series on burnout. Two years ago, I told my then co-founder Eelco that I would leave the company in a few months. I didn&amp;#8217;t have a lot of fun programming anymore. We were a consulting company, building iPhone apps for clients.
We started the company during our Master&amp;#8217;s, where we would program in Haskell all the time. However, iPhone apps are built in Objective C, which is almost the opposite in language design: Objective C is designed to be very practical and with a lot of low-level control, whereas Haskell started as a pure, math-like language and moved towards a more practical language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lots of Test Projects</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lots-of-test-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/lots-of-test-projects/</guid>
      <description>This might be a trivial thing, and I might be stupid for not having done with it all my life, but this was a big insight for me. Only a few months ago, I really started making lots of small test projects to only test out a specific feature or solution. For example, I have a project that implements UITableViewCells with XIBs, a test project for working with local notifications, a test project to play around with rotation events and more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A month of blogging</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/a-month-of-blogging/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/a-month-of-blogging/</guid>
      <description>As a tribute to Gabriel Weinberg&amp;#8217;s Why I Blog, here&amp;#8217;s my experience about starting and committing to this blog. Even though I&amp;#8217;ve only been blogging for a month, it&amp;#8217;s already been a tremendous experience. Now that I&amp;#8217;m the rythm of writing a small article every workday, it seems hard to break that chain of posts.
Helps you understand
I couldn&amp;#8217;t agree more with Gabriel, writing helps to understand yourself. Vague feelings have to be expressed using clear language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Minimalism</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/on-minimalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/on-minimalism/</guid>
      <description>A few years ago, I first read Stuff by Paul Graham. The article really resonated with me, even though I was living in a small room at the time and didn&amp;#8217;t have that much stuff. In recent months, I have been discussing similar topics with some of my friends, philosofying about Minimalism, Stoicism and Buddhism. Since then, I have been actively trying to get rid of more stuff and making my life simpler in general.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selecting which apps to build</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/selecting-which-apps-to-build/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/selecting-which-apps-to-build/</guid>
      <description>I have a huge list of ideas for iPhone apps (and lots of other ideas). When I last counted, there were over a hundred items on my list. How do I select which apps to build?
Marketing
First of all, I need a way to do marketing. It helps a lot if it is a niche product. For example, I have an idea for a very cool iOS marketplace site, but it will be nearly impossible for me to do the marketing, as it is targeted at everybody with an iPhone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 iPhone apps for backpackers</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/10-iphone-apps-for-backpackers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/10-iphone-apps-for-backpackers/</guid>
      <description>In this article I share with you the 10 apps that I used most during backpacking. With these apps you&amp;#8217;ll travel without missing your laptop. If you have any more favorite apps, please send them to me!
Camera - Free
This app is already installed, but there are some handy tricks for getting more out of it when traveling. You can take pictures of timetables in railway stations, pictures of maps (for example, floor plans or city maps) and pictures of things you want to remember.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Start Small, Stay Small</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/book-review-start-small-stay-small/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/book-review-start-small-stay-small/</guid>
      <description>This blog post will be a bit different from previous ones: a book review. Before I went on a two week holiday I got a lot of responses to my previous articles from awesome Hacker News community members. Jim Walker recommended me the book &#34;Start Small, Stay Small: A Developer&amp;#8217;s guide to launching a startup&#34;. I immediately bought it on my Kindle (it&amp;#8217;s only $11) and started reading in the plane to Romania.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Off on a holiday</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/off-on-a-holiday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/off-on-a-holiday/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#8217;m off to Romania, for a well-deserved holiday. We don&amp;#8217;t have a set plan, but will probably spend some time in Bucharest and at the Black Sea. I&amp;#8217;ll have lots of time to read and think, really looking forward to it!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I shipped my first product</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/i-shipped-my-first-product/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/i-shipped-my-first-product/</guid>
      <description>Today, the first version of TrackMe is available from the App Store. This is my first product as an indie developer, and even though it&amp;#8217;s very simple, I&amp;#8217;m proud to have gone through the cycle of getting the idea, building it and releasing it.
As you can read in my post The Big Plan, one of the things I find difficult is shipping software. Specifically: my own software. It&amp;#8217;s different when you build something for a client or for a boss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good coffeeshops in Berlin</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/good-coffeeshops-in-berlin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/good-coffeeshops-in-berlin/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;#8217;re a digital nomad, you are always looking for good places to work. In Berlin, there are a couple of good places with good wifi and coffee. Here is a list of the places where I like to work.
St. Oberholz - Rosenthaler Strasse 72
This is the place for a digital nomad. They serve excellent coffee, have good food and it is well known for being friendly towards people with laptops.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to succeed as a freelance developer</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-to-succeed-as-a-freelance-developer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/how-to-succeed-as-a-freelance-developer/</guid>
      <description>In this article, I will share some tips on how to succeed as a freelance developer. This is only a short list, and there is a lot more to it. As a precondition, it is important to know your tools. Make sure you can deliver. Once you&amp;#8217;re ready to take on jobs, you can do any of the things below. Note that most work on the long term. It&amp;#8217;s not uncommon that somebody hires or recommends you more than a year after you met her for the first time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I want to become rich</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/why-i-want-to-become-rich/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/why-i-want-to-become-rich/</guid>
      <description>My ambition is to become a millionaire by the time I&amp;#8217;m 30 years old. That gives me about 3.5 more years to accomplish that goal. Even though I&amp;#8217;m really happy where I am now and have enough money to live off, I still aim for bigger things.
The reason is not that I want to have more expensive houses or more stuff. I&amp;#8217;m not a sucker for luxury (yet?). In fact, I&amp;#8217;ve been reducing the amount of stuff I own considerably, living out of a suitcase and planning to live out of a backpack.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I develop for iOS</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/why-i-develop-for-ios/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/why-i-develop-for-ios/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes I ask myself the question: why do I develop for iOS? I could also do Haskell development, do cool HTML5 stuff, or build compilers. As an indie developer, these are some important reasons for me.
High-end platform
The iPhone and iPad are the high-end of the smartphones and tablets. This means that the people who use it are willing to pay more money for a better experience. As a side effect, they are also willing to pay for apps, and willing to pay for in-app purchases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plan it the night before</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/plan-it-the-night-before/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/plan-it-the-night-before/</guid>
      <description>About a week ago, I read this interview with Andrew Hsu. He said one of his ways to be productive is making your todo-list the night before. I&amp;#8217;ve tried this for a few days now, and it seems to work. For the last few day, I really got a lot done.
One of the reasons why I think it works is because it can help you focus on the right tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Berlin</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/on-berlin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/on-berlin/</guid>
      <description>Ever since I first got to Berlin, about 7 years ago, I fell in love with the city. Four years ago I spent my first summer in Berlin, living in Prenzlauer Berg. The city offers all I wanted: awesome parties, cheap rents, easy to find a house, very diverse but low-priced food, lots of other young people, very laid back and quite alternative.
Now it&amp;#8217;s 2011, and I love Berlin even more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Big Plan</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/the-big-plan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/the-big-plan/</guid>
      <description>When I was 15, I started my first job as a web developer. I worked for a local computer repair shop, and the clients needed websites, so I designed and built them. I built my first CMS, which my boss dubbed IWOS: Internet Web Online System. I guess that I already learned at that time that having a boss can suck. Fast forward 11 years later, I have had numerous development jobs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 day experiment: no more sugar</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/no-more-sugar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/no-more-sugar/</guid>
      <description>Ever since I heard about 30 day challenges, I have loved the idea. About 6 weeks ago, it was time for a new 30 day challenge: cutting out sugar. I have been a sugar addict for a long time: I can always eat sugary stuff and have a constant craving. I thought that this would be the hardest thing I had ever done (and I&amp;#8217;ve done things like running a half marathon).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing a MySQL database with R</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/analyzing-a-mysql-database-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/analyzing-a-mysql-database-with-r/</guid>
      <description>In this article, we analyze a MySQL database which contains soccer transfer data, using the R environment, on OS X. We show in a few simple steps how you can link the two together.
  Prerequisites
Make sure you have a recent version of MySQL, and the latest version of R installed. As our graphical user interface, we use RStudio. From RStudio you can install the MySQL package: install.packages(&#34;RMySQL&#34;). If this doesn&amp;#8217;t work for you, please refer to the installation instructions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://chris.eidhof.nl/post/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>From this new tumblr I&amp;#8217;ll be posting my random ramblings.
{% endblock body %} </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>